Guide to the Mary Cadwalader Jones Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mary Cadwalader Jones correspondence
1876-1934
YCAL MSS 409
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The Mary Cadwalader Jones Correspondence contains letters from various individuals, including notable writers, poets, politicians, and artists, including Edith Wharton, Grover Cleveland, Ruth Draper, Edgar Lee Masters, Augustus Saint-Gaudens, Nikola Tesla, and H.G. Wells.
Jones, Mary Cadwalader
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from 7 Gables on the Danford Barney Fund, 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Mary Cadwalader Jones
Mary Cadwalader Jones, writer, literary agent, and sister-in-law of author Edith Wharton. Jones grew up in a wealthy Philadelphia family and married Frederic Rhinelander Jones, Edith Wharton's oldest brother, in 1872. The couple moved to New York City and had a daughter named Beatrix. The marriage lasted twelve years and the couple divorced. In New York, Jones was well-known for hosting Sunday afternoon lunches at her house attended by notable literary figures, such as Edith Wharton and Henry James.
During her life, Jones published two books and many articles concerning the welfare of nurses and medical system reform. She was active in the development of the New York City Hospital School and served as the chair for the Advisory Board on Nursing. She vacationed in Bar Harbor, Maine where she volunteered with the local schools and collaborated with residents to create Acadia National Park.
Scope and Contents
The Mary Cadwalader Jones Correspondence contains letters from various individuals, including notable writers, poets, politicians, and artists, such as Edith Wharton, Grover Cleveland, Ruth Draper, Edgar Lee Masters, Augustus Saint-Gaudens, Nikola Tesla, and H.G. Wells. The correspondence includes a typescript draft of "A 'Rarebit' of Biography" by unidentified author.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908; Draper, Ruth, 1884-1956; Jones, Mary Cadwalader; Masters, Edgar Lee, 1868-1950; Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1848-1907; Tesla, Nikola, 1856-1943; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946; Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937
- Mary Cadwalader Jones Correspondence, 1876-1934
  Arrangement
  Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. A vendor list is filed at the beginning of the box.
  - Akins, Zoe, 1921 March 15 (Box 1)
  - Allen, Vivla, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Anglin, Margaret, undated (Box 1)
  - Bancroft, George, 1876 January 24 (Box 1)
  - Barrymore, Ethel, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Beith, John Hay, 1916 October 17 (Box 1)
  - Belmont, Eleanor R., undated (Box 1)
  - Berenson, Bernhard, 1918-1935 (Box 1)
  - Bigelow, Poultney, 1917 March 12 (Box 1)
  - Blashfield, Edwin H., 1916 June 17 (Box 1)
  - Bridges, Robert, 1912 February 20 (Box 1)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Bryce, James, 1921 December 2 (Box 1)
  - Byron Library, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Childs, George W., 1876 April 29 (Box 1)
  - Cleveland, Grover, 1884 October 26 (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Francis Marion, 1903-1909, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Curtis, George William, 1879 March 17 (Box 1)
  - Damrosch, Walter, 1908 March 12 (Box 1)
  - De la Pasture, E. M., 1909 (Box 1)
  - Deland, Margaret, 1916 September 12 (Box 1)
  - Draper, Ruth, 1929-1933 (Box 1)
  - Drew, John, undated (Box 1)
  - Drinkwater, John, 1920 February 21 (Box 1)
  - Ervine, St. John, 1933 February 13 (Box 1)
  - Fay, Bernard, 1923 November 13 (Box 1)
  - Fish, Stuyvesant, undated (Box 1)
  - Fiske, Minnie Madern, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Fitch, Clyde, 1905 February 22 (Box 1)
  - Forbes-Robertson, 1914 February 2 (Box 1)
  - Garland, Hamlin, undated (Box 1)
  - Gaynor, William, 1909 May 9 (Box 1)
  - Godkin, Edwin L, undated (Box 1)
  - Grant, Robert, 1914 October (Box 1)
  - Guthrie, T. Ansley, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Hadley, Arthur, 1900 July 10 (Box 1)
  - Harrison, Henry Sydnor, 1915 December 22 (Box 1)
  - Hay, John, 1891 (Box 1)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1929 December 17 (Box 1)
  - Howe, Julia Ward, 1901 December 29 (Box 1)
  - Huntington, Archer, 1934 December 23 (Box 1)
  - Huxley, Julian, 1931 January 28 (Box 1)
  - James, William, 1909 December 5 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Henry Arthur, 1914 November 25 (Box 1)
  - Kaneko, Kentaro, 1904 January 26 (Box 1)
  - LaFarge, John, 1904 August 16 (Box 1)
  - Le Gallienne, Eva, 1933 March 7 (Box 1)
  - Leland, Charles Godfrey, 1884 May 19 (Box 1)
  - Lindsay, Ronald, 1931 December 27 (Box 1)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1919-1921 (Box 1)
  - Mahan, Alfred Thayer, 1897 February 1 (Box 1)
  - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Matthews, Brander, 1896 (Box 1)
  - Maugham, W. Somerset, 1910 November 26 (Box 1)
  - McDowell, Edward, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Merivale, Philip, 1932 January 29 (Box 1)
  - Mitchell, Silas Weir, undated (Box 1)
  - Osborne, Lloyd, 1902 (Box 1)
  - Pennell, Joseph, 1900-1901 (Box 1)
  - Pennington, Harper, 1902 August 18 (Box 1)
  - Reed, Thomas B., 1892 February 6 (Box 1)
  - Rhodes, Harrison, 1909 October 19 (Box 1)
  - Rocca, Giovanni, 1910 November 25 (Box 1)
  - Root, Elihu, 1907, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Saint-Gaudens, Augustus, 1903 (Box 1)
  - Satterlee, Henry Y., 1899 August 25 (Box 1)
  - Scott, Geoffrey, 1929 February 15 (Box 1)
  - Scott, Winfield, undated (Box 1)
  - Sharp, William, circa 1901 (Box 1)
  - Sheldon, Edward, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Sherman, William Tecumseh, 1889 April 14 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Logan Permsall, 1933 August 11 (Box 1)
  - Stead, William Thomas, 1911 May 24 (Box 1)
  - Stevenson, Fanny, 1903 December 14 (Box 1)
  - Stone, Melville E., 1917 April 17 (Box 1)
  - Strachey, John St. Loe, 1917 January 6 (Box 1)
  - Taft, William Howard, 1911 June 13 (Box 1)
  - Terry, Ellen, 1899 April 14 (Box 1)
  - Tesla, Nikola, 1907 January 15 (Box 1)
  - Tree, Herbert Beerbohm, 1896 December 25 (Box 1)
  - Trevelyan, George M., 1909 February 5, 1915 April 25 (Box 1)
  - Trevelyan, George Otto, 1915 April 25 (Box 1)
  - Troubetzkoy, Amelie (Rives), undated (Box 1)
  - Updike, Berkeley, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Van Dyke, Henry, 1911 August 16 (Box 1)
  - Ward, Mary, 1903, 1915 (Box 1)
  - Wells, H. G., 1906 April 4 (Box 1)
  - Wharton, Edith, 1903 November 25 (Box 1)
  - Wierzbicki, Comte de, undated (Box 1)
  - Wiggin, Kate Douglas, 1915 (Box 1)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1909 March 15, 1909 April 21 (Box 1)
  - Wister, Owen, 1916 October 31 (Box 1)
  - Young, Stark, 1934 (Box 1)
  - "A 'Rarebit' of Biography." Typescript draft with illustration, unidentified author, undated (Box 1)